<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of Sr. Edw. Turnor, Kt., speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty delivered on Monday the nineteeth day of May, 1662, at the prorogation of the Parliament.</title>
            <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12244330</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12244330</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56859</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56859)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of Sr. Edw. Turnor, Kt., speaker of the honourable House of Commons, to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty delivered on Monday the nineteeth day of May, 1662, at the prorogation of the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Turnor, Edward, Sir, 1617-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D. Maxwell for Henry Twyford, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political oratory --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56859:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <p>THE SPEECH OF S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edw. Turnor, K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS, TO THE KINGS Moſt Excellent MAJESTY, <hi>Delivered on Monday the Nineteenth day of</hi> May, 1662. <hi>at the Prorogation of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>D. Maxwell</hi> for <hi>Henry Twyford,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Vine-Court, Middle-Temple. 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:56859:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56859:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <head>THE SPEECH OF S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> EDW. TURNOR, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <head type="sub">Delivered on Monday the Nineteenth day of <hi>May</hi> 1662. at the Proroguing the PARLAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your moſt Excellent Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He glorious body of the Sun doth exhillerate the ſoul of Man with its light, and fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the earth by its heat: In like manner, We the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Commons Houſe of Parliament, do with all humility and thankfulneſſe acknowledge, theſe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acceſsions to Your Royal Preſence,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56859:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->do both comfort our hearts, and influence our actions.</p>
            <p>Geographers do tell us, The Land of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> is a dry Soile, but made fertile by the overflowing of the River <hi>Nylus;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the degrees of the Floud, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants do prognoſticate the fruitfulneſs of the enſuing year, if it flows to twelve de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, it preſages a good Harveſt; if to thirteen, then more plentifull; but if to four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen degrees, their hopes are raiſed to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of an abundant encreaſe.</p>
            <p>Great Sir, your return into this Nation in the twelfth year of your Reign, reſembles the flowing of the River <hi>Nilus</hi> in the twelfth Degree; That year was Crowned with the enjoyment of your Royal Perſon. The laſt year being the Thirteenth year of your Majeſties Reign, we were made happy in Your Coronation, and by Your Sanction of many good and uſefull Lawes both for the Church and State. And now our River <hi>Nilus</hi> begins to flow fourteen Degrees, we are by the mercies of God in an humble ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a great Jubilee. Our Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queen is now happily landed, who we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56859:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->do hope, and dayly pray, may prove a ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Companion to Your Royal Perſon, and ere long a Nurſing Mother to this Nation.</p>
            <p>If Your Majeſty but pleaſe to caſt Your Eyes upon the Table, and behold the great number of Bills that there preſent themſelves before You, like ſo many ſheafs of Corn bound up and ready to be houſed; and will vouchſafe to ſee how both my hands are filled with no light Preſents from Your Loyal Commons; and if Your Royal Majeſty, the great Lord of the Harveſt, ſhall vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to Crown this Day by Your gracious Conceſsions to our Deſires, the world will then ſee how great a duty Your people cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pay both to Your Royal Perſon and Your Government, and likewiſe how great a Zeal Your Majeſty hath, by the faithfull Advice of the Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and Commons Aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to Settle the Church in her Ancient Glory, and to reſtore the happy People of this Nation to their ancient Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
            <p>Some Forreign Writers, that envy the happineſs of our Government, injuriouſly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56859:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->aſperſe this Nation with a reproachful Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That the Crown of</hi> England <hi>is only main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the benevolence of the people, which never is granted, but in exchange of ſome Royal Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great Sir,</p>
            <p>We know the ſtrongeſt Building muſt fall, if the coupling Pins be pulled out; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our care hath been to prepare ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, that the Prerogative of the Crown, and the Propriety of the People, may like ſquared Stones in a well-built Arch, each ſupport the other, and grow the cloſer and ſtronger for any weight or force that ſhall be laid upon them.</p>
            <p>We cannot forget the late Diſputing Age, wherein moſt perſons took a liberty, and ſome men made it their delight, to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon the Diſcipline and Government of the Church; the Hedg being trod down, the Foxes and the Wolves did enter, the Swine and other unclean beaſts defiled the Temple: at length it was diſcerned, the <hi>Smectymnian</hi> Plot did not only bend it ſelf to reform Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, but ſought to erect a popular Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Elders, and to root out Epiſcopal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56859:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->Juriſdiction: In order to this Work, Church-Ornaments were firſt taken away, then the Means whereby Diſtinction or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality might be upheld amongſt Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Governors; then the forms of Common-Prayer, which, as Members of the publick Body of Chriſts Church, were enjoined us, were decryed as Superſtitious, and in lieu thereof, nothing, or worſe then nothing, introduced. Your Majeſty having already reſtored the Governors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, the Patrimony and Priviledges of our Church-men, We held it now our duty, for the Reformation of all abuſes in the Publick Worſhip of God, Humbly to preſent unto Your Majeſty, a Bill for <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of Publick Prayers, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We hope the God of Order and Unity will conform the hearts of all the people in this Nation, to ſerve him in this Order and Uniformity.</p>
            <p>Next to the Worſhip and Service of God, We applied our ſelves to the ſetling our great Concern, the Militia. We have already, according to our duties, and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56859:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->Laws, declared the Sole right of the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia to be in Your Majeſty: And now with Your Permiſsion, VVe humbly tender Your Majeſty a Bill for the better Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Ordering the ſtanding Forces of this Nation: wherein VVe have taken care, to make all things ſo certain, that Your Majeſties Lieutenants and their Deputies, may know what to Command, and all the people learn how to obey.</p>
            <p>And becauſe our late Wounds are yet but green, and poſſibly before the body Politick be well purged, may incline to break out again, whereby Your Majeſty may be forced to draw Your Sword before Your Treaſury be ſupplied with money: We have conſented that Your Majeſty may raiſe for the three next enſuing years, one months Tax in each year, after the rate of 70000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per menſem,</hi> if neceſſity ſhall ſo require.</p>
            <p>In the next place, according to Your Majeſties Commands, we have ſurveyed the waſted Revenue of the Crown; and in purſuance of our promiſes, do humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto your Majeſty a fair addition:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56859:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->We conſidered that great part of Your Majeſties Revenue is but for life; and both that, and alſo part of the reſt depends upon the Peace, the Trade, and Traffick of the Nation, and therefore may be much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by Wars with forreign Nations: This put us upon the ſearch of ſomething that might ariſe within our own walls, and not be ſubject to ſuch contingencies: We pitcht our thoughts at laſt upon thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where we enjoy our greateſt comforts and ſecurities, our dwelling houſes: and conſidering even that ſecurity is ſecured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by Your Majeſties vigilance and care in the Government; We have prepared a Bill, whereby We deſire it may be enacted, <hi>That all Houſes in this Kingdom, which are worth in yearly value above Twenty ſhillings, and not inhabited by Almeſmen, may pay unto Your Majeſty, Your Heirs and Succeſſors, two ſhillings yearly, for every Chimney-hearth in each houſe for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the great <hi>Ahithophels</hi> of our latter Age had by force raviſhed the venerable Laws of this Nation, <hi>(uno abſurdo dato, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur milia,)</hi> then every petty Artiſt in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56859:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->his way, yea even the very common Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars had the Confidence to offer violence to their Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>We have therefore been conſtrained to prepare ſeveral Bills for the Regulation of Trade, our Cloathing Trade, our Fiſhing Trade, our Trade for Stuffs, our Trade for Silks; and for the better maintenance of intercourſe in Trade, to re-inforce our former Laws for maintaining the High-ways, with ſome Additions for decency and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Travellers</p>
            <p>God in his Providence hath determined, <hi>That Poor we muſt have always with us;</hi> ſome are made ſo by the immedia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Hand of God: others by their Loyalty, Duty and Service of Your Royal Perſon and Your Bleſſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: others by their own wickedneſs and idleneſs: We have taken care to relieve the firſt, to encourage the ſecond, and to reform the laſt.</p>
            <p>Nor hath the Caſe of any private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon been unwelcome to us; thoſe many Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Bills that lie before Your Majeſty do enough confirm this Truth, That where we found it Juſt and Honorable, We have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56859:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->denied our helping hand to none that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it</p>
            <p>And now, Great Sir, after theſe many Months moſt painfull and faithfull Service of Your Majeſty and our Countreys, we hope we ſhall have leave to go home, to viſit our Relations, to tell our Neighbours, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t great things Your Majeſty hath done for Us, what great things <hi>(abſit invidia verbo)</hi> we have done for Your Majeſty, and what great things God hath done for Us all; and to pray Almighty God for his Mercy to this Nation, in the continuance of Your Majeſties Long and Happy Reign over us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
